<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Circe</title>
          <author>Augusta Webster</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt><p>TEASys Viewer</p></publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc><p>Annotating Literature, Tübingen University</p></sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><anchor xml:id="s-circe"/><anchor xml:id="e-circe"/>The sun drops <anchor xml:id="s-luridly"/>luridly<anchor xml:id="e-luridly"/> into the west;
darkness has raised her arms to draw him down
before the time, not waiting as of wont
till he has come to her behind the sea;
and the smooth waves grow sullen in the gloom
and wear their threatening purple; more and more
the plain of waters sways and seems to rise
convexly from its level of the shores;
and low dull thunder rolls along the beach:
<anchor xml:id="s-there-will-be-storm-at-last-storm-glorious-storm"/>there will be storm at last, storm, glorious storm.<anchor xml:id="e-there-will-be-storm-at-last-storm-glorious-storm"/>

Oh welcome, welcome, though it rend my bowers,
scattering my blossomed roses like the dust,
splitting the shrieking branches, tossing down
my riotous vines with their young half-tinged grapes
like small round <anchor xml:id="s-amethysts-or-beryls"/>amethysts or beryls<anchor xml:id="e-amethysts-or-beryls"/> strung
tumultuously in clusters, though it sate
its ravenous spite among my goodliest pines
standing there round and still against the sky
that makes blue lakes between their sombre tufts,
or harry from my silvery olive slopes
some hoary king whose gnarled fantastic limbs
wear crooked armour of a thousand years;
though it will hurl high on my flowery shores
the hostile wave that rives at the poor <anchor xml:id="s-sward"/>sward<anchor xml:id="e-sward"/>
and drags it down the slants, that swirls its foam
over my terraces, shakes their firm blocks
of great bright marbles into tumbled heaps,
and makes my preached and mossy labyrinths,
where the small odorous blossoms grow like stars
strewn in the milky way, a briny marsh.
What matter? let it come and bring me change,
breaking the sickly sweet <anchor xml:id="s-monotony"/>monotony<anchor xml:id="e-monotony"/>.

I am too weary of this long bright calm;
always the same blue sky, always the sea
the same blue perfect likeness of the sky,
one rose to match the other that has waned,
to-morrow&apos;s dawn the twin of yesterday&apos;s;
and every night the ceaseless crickets chirp
the same long joy and the late strain of birds
repeats their strain of all the even month;
and changelessly the petty plashing surfs
bubble their chiming burden round the stones;
dusk after dusk brings the same languid trance
upon the shadowy hills, and in the fields
the waves of fireflies come and go the same,
making the very flash of light and stir
vex one like dronings of the spinning wheel.

Give me some change. Must life be only sweet,
all honey-pap as babes would have their food?
And, if my heart must always be adrowse
in a hush of stagnant sunshine, give me then
something outside me stirring; let the storm
break up the sluggish beauty, let it fall
beaten below the feet of passionate winds,
and then to-morrow waken jubilant
in a new birth: let me see subtle joy
of anguish and of hopes, of change and growth.

What fate is mine who, far apart from pains
and fears and turmoils of the cross-grained world,
dwell, like a lonely god, in a charmed isle
where I am first and only, and, like one
who should love poisonous savours more than mead,
long for a tempest on me and grow sick
of resting, and divine free carelessness!
Oh me, I am a woman, not a god;
yea, those who tend me even are more than I,
my nymphs who have the souls of flowers and birds
singing and blossoming immortally.

Ah me! these love a day and laugh again,
and loving, laughing, find a full content;
but I know nought of peace, and have not loved.

Where is my love? Does some one cry for me,
not knowing whom he calls? does his soul cry
for mine to grow beside it, grow in it?
does he beseech the gods to give him me,
the one unknown rare woman by whose side
no other woman, thrice as beautiful,
should once seem fair to him; to whose voice heard
in any common tones no sweetest sound
of love made melody on silver lutes,
or singing like Apollo&apos;s when the gods
grow pale with happy listening, might be peered
for making music to him; whom once found
there will be no more seeking anything?

Oh love, oh love, oh love, art not yet come
out of the waiting shadows into life?
art not yet come after so many years
that I have longed for thee? Come! I am here.

Not yet. For surely I should feel a sound
of his far answering, if now in the world
he sought me who will seek me—Oh ye gods
will he not seek me? Is it all a dream?
will there be never never such a man?
will there be only these, these bestial things
who wallow in my styes, or mop and mow
among the trees, or munch in pens and byres,
or snarl and filch behind their wattled coops;
these things who had believed that they were men?

Nay but he will come. Why am I so fair,
and marvellously minded, and with sight
which flashes suddenly on hidden things,
as the gods see who do not need to look?
why wear I in my eyes that stronger power
than basilisks, whose gaze can only kill,
to draw men&apos;s souls to me to live or die
as I would have them? why am I given pride
which yet longs to be broken, and this scorn
cruel and vengeful for the lesser men
who meet the smiles I waste for lack of him
and grow too glad? why am I who I am,
but for the sake of him whom fate will send
one day to be my master utterly,
that he should take me, the desire of all,
whom only he in the world could bow to him?

Oh sunlike glory of pale glittering hairs,
bright as the filmy wires my weavers take
to make me golden gauzes; oh deep eyes,
darker and softer than the bluest dusk
of August violets, darker and deep
like crystal fathomless lakes in summer noons;
oh sad sweet longing smile; oh lips that tempt
my very self to kisses; oh round cheeks,
tenderly radiant with the even flush
of pale smoothed coral; perfect lovely face
answering my gaze from out this fleckless pool;
wonder of glossy shoulders, chiselled limbs;
should I be so your lover as I am,
drinking an exquisite joy to watch you thus
in all a hundred changes through the day,
but that I love you for him till he comes,
but that my beauty means his loving it?

Oh, look! a speck on this side of the sun,
coming—yes, coming with the rising wind
that frays the darkening cloud-wrack on the verge
and in a little while will leap abroad,
spattering the sky with rushing blacknesses,
dashing the hissing mountainous waves at the stars.
&apos;Twill drive me that black speck a shuddering hulk
caught in the buffeting waves, dashed impotent
from ridge to ridge, will drive it in the night
with that dull jarring crash upon the beach,
and the cries for help and the cries of fear and hope.

And then to-morrow they will thoughtfully,
with grave low voices, count their perils up,
and thank the gods for having let them live,
and tell of wives or mothers in their homes,
and children, who would have such loss in them
that they must weep, and may be I weep too,
with fancy of the weepings had they died.
And the next morrow they will feel their ease
and sigh with sleek content, or laugh elate,
tasting delights of rest and revelling,
music and perfumes, joyaunce for the eyes
of rosy faces and luxurious pomps,
the savour of the banquet and the glow
and fragrance of the wine-cup; and they&apos;ll talk
how good it is to house in palaces
out of the storms and struggles, and what luck
strewed their good ship on our accessless coast.
Then the next day the beast in them will wake,
and one will strike and bicker, and one swell
with puffed up greatness, and one gibe and strut
in apish pranks, and one will line his sleeve
with <anchor xml:id="s-pilfered-booties"/>pilfered booties<anchor xml:id="e-pilfered-booties"/>, and one snatch the gems
out of the carven goblets as they pass,
one will grow mad with fever of the wine,
and one will sluggishly besot himself,
and one be lewd, and one be gluttonous;
and I shall sickly look, and loathe them all.

Oh my rare cup! my pure and crystal cup,
with not one speck of colour to make false
the passing lights, or flaw to make them swerve!
My cup of Truth! How the lost fools will laugh
and thank me for my boon, as if I gave
some momentary flash of the gods&apos; joy,
to drink where I have drunk and touch the touch
of my lips with their own! Aye, let them touch.

Too cruel am I? And the silly beasts,
crowding around me when I pass their way,
glower on me and, although they love me still,
(with their poor sorts of love such as they could,)
call wrath and vengeance to their humid eyes
to scare me into mercy, or creep near
with piteous fawnings, supplicating bleats.
Too cruel? Did I choose them what they are?
or change them from themselves by poisonous charms?
But any draught, pure water, natural wine,
out of my cup, revealed them to themselves
and to each other. Change? there was no change;
only disguise gone from them unawares:
and had there been one right true man of them
he would have drunk the draught as I had drunk,
and stood unchanged, and looked me in the eyes,
abashing me before him. But these things—
why, which of them has even shown the kind
of some one nobler beast? Pah, yapping wolves
and pitiless stealthy wild-cats, curs and apes
and gorging swine and slinking venomous snakes
all false and ravenous and sensual brutes
that shame the Earth that bore them, these they are.

Lo, lo! the shivering blueness darting forth
on half the heavens, and the forked thin fire
strikes to the sea: and hark, the sudden voice
that rushes through the trees before the storm,
and shuddering of the branches. Yet the sky
is blue against them still, and early stars
glimmer above the pine-tops; and the air
clings faint and motionless around me here.

Another burst of flame—and the black speck
shows in the glare, lashed onwards. It were well
I bade make ready for our guests to-night.</div></body></text>
  <standOff>
      <listAnnotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-amethysts-or-beryls" from="#s-amethysts-or-beryls" to="#e-amethysts-or-beryls">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Isabel Maria Osuna Montilla</name><name>Sophia Smolinski</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-20</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#language">
                  <p>These are two kinds of precious stones. Whereas “amethyst” is a “[q]uartz of a violet or purple variety” (“amethyst, *n*. and *adj*.” A.1.a.), “beryl” is described as having “a pale-green colour passing into light-blue, yellow, and white; distinguished only by colour from the more precious emerald” (“beryl, *n*. and *adj*.” A.I.1.a.).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>“amethyst, *n*. and *adj*.” *OED Online*, Oxford University Press, December 2021, www.oed.com/view/Entry/6366. Accessed 2 December 2021.</bibl><bibl>“beryl, *n*. and *adj*.” *OED Online*, Oxford University Press, December 2021, www.oed.com/view/Entry/18007. Accessed 2 December 2021.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#form">
                  <p>The stones are part of a simile. They are compared to the grapes of the previous line whose destruction the speaker would accept as a consequence of change (cf. [[storm]]).</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#interpretation">
                  <p>The simile highlights the colour and, potentially, ripeness, of the grapes, creating a mental image of shiny purple and green grapes mixed together. The comparison intimates the island’s lushness and fertility.</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-circe" from="#s-circe" to="#e-circe">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Isabel Maria Osuna Montilla</name><name>Sophia Smolinski</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-20</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#context">
                  <p>The poem “Circe” is included in Portraits (1870), together with other poems, such as “Medea in Athens”, that are also written in the form of a dramatic monologue by a female speaker (cf. Level 1 Form).
The title of the poem refers to Greek mythology: Circe is the daughter of Helios (the Titan sun god) and Perse (one of the Oceanids), and she is considered a powerful enchantress.</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#form">
                  <p>“Circe” is written in the form of a dramatic monologue, which means that Circe herself is the speaker of the poem.</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#form">
                  <p>The [dramatic monologue](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dramatic_monologue) finds its roots in the Romantic period and reached a peak in popularity during the Victorian era; it was made particularly popular by [Robert Browning](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Browning) (“dramatic monologue”). 
Circe as the speaker of the dramatic monologue allows for an unusually frank presentation of female desire, especially given the rather strict norms of behaviour in the Victorian era. When referring to the Medea and Circe poems, Christine Sutphin points out that “[t]heir apparent cultural and mythical distance gives them the power to critique heterosexual politics and to express their own desires in ways impossible for Victorian personae” (17). The three poems in Webster’s collection that are titled with names (“Medea in Athens”, “Circe” and “The Manuscript of Saint Alexius”) are the only ones that refer to a distant past. 
With the name “Circe”, Webster is also able to create a reference to other nineteenth-century poems, such as Matthew Arnold’s “The Strayed Reveller” or Tennyson’s “Ulysses”, that also re-examine this specific classical myth (Houston 9), albeit from a different (as in male) perspective.</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>“dramatic monologue.” *A Dictionary of Literary Terms and Literary Theory*, edited by John A. Cuddon, 5th ed., Wiley-Blackwell, 2013.</bibl><bibl>Houston, Natalie M. “Order and Interpretation in Augusta Webster’s Portraits.” *Romanticism and Victorianism on the Net*, no. 47, August 2007, pars. 1-25, doi.org/10.7202/016701ar.</bibl><bibl>Sutphin, Christine. “Introduction.” *Augusta Webster: Portraits and Other Poems*, by Sutphin, Broadview Press Ltd., 2000, pp. 9-37.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#context">
                  <p>Circe appears in book ten of Homer’s *The Odyssey*. After landing on Circe’s Island (Aeaea), Odysseus tells his men to explore it. They discover Circe’s house where they drink from a magic cup that she offers them. The potion from the cup transforms them into pigs. When Odysseus reaches the house, he is already protected by a spell thanks to an herb given to him by the god Hermes. He confronts Circe and convinces her to restore his men to their human forms. Odysseus and Circe become lovers, and she then helps him find his way back home.

Circe also appears in book four of Apollonius’ *Argonautica*, where she assists Jason and her niece Medea by acquitting them from the murder they have committed. Another mention of Circe is in the myth of the mortal king Picus whom, out of spite, she transforms into a woodpecker. In the story of the sea-god Glaucus and the nymph Scylla, Circe turns Scylla into a monster by poisoning the water Scylla usually takes her bath in. To read more about these two myths, see Ovid’s *Metamorphoses* Book XIV, edited by K. Sara Myers, Cambridge UP, 2009.</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Ovid. *Metamorphoses Book XIV*. Edited by K. Sara Myers, Cambridge UP, 2009.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-luridly" from="#s-luridly" to="#e-luridly">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Isabel Maria Osuna Montilla</name><name>Sophia Smolinski</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-20</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#language">
                  <p>Usually, “lurid” describes something “[p]ale and dismal in colour” (“lurid, *adj*.” 1.); here, it is used to describe the colour of the sky at sunset: “[s]hining with a red glow or glare amid darkness” (“lurid, *adj*.” 2.a.).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>“lurid, *adj.*” 1. and 2.a. *OED Online*, Oxford University Press, December 2021, www.oed.com/view/Entry/111313. Accessed 17 February 2022.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-monotony" from="#s-monotony" to="#e-monotony">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Isabel Maria Osuna Montilla</name><name>Sophia Smolinski</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-20</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#language">
                  <p>“Sweet” in this context is synonymous with “pleas[ant]” (“sweet, *adj*. and *adv*.” 5). “Sickly” can be explained with being “[t]horoughly tired or weary of a thing”, in this case of supposedly pleasant monotony (“sick *adj*. and *n*.” 5.a.).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>“sick, *adj*. and *n*.” *OED Online*, Oxford University Press, March 2022, www.oed.com/view/Entry/179187. Accessed 15 April 2022.</bibl><bibl>“sweet”, *adj*. and *adv*.” *OED Online*, Oxford University Press, March 2022, www. oed.com/view/Entry/195665. Accessed 15 April 2022.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#intratextuality">
                  <p>The speaker frequently refers to herself as being stuck in a state of monotony: the landscape of Circe’s island is described as unchangeable (see lines 33-47), and Circe’s own life is presented as dull and uneventful (see lines 58-65).</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#interpretation">
                  <p>The combination of contradictory words preceding “monotony” emphasises Circe’s rejection of a sweet monotonous life, since this sweetness is exhausting and irritating her. 
The speaker in “Circe” longs to break the “sickly sweet monotony” of her stagnant life and to subject herself to and enjoy the passions that a storm, may bring: see lines 58-65. This yearning for action is highlighted by Circe’s description of the island’s unchanging cycle of life (cf. [[storm]]). 
The state of monotony can also be understood to describe Circe’s uneventful love life. The storm, then as a metaphor, stands for the passions that she hopes the ship-wrecked sailors can incite within her.</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#context">
                  <p>In the context of mid-Victorian debates about the role of (especially middle-class) women in society, Circe’s desire to break the monotony of her life may be an echo of the voices of women in Webster’s time that were demanding more emotional and mental stimulation (Fiske 486). Indeed, Circe’s claim for action in her life (see line 65) resonates with Nightingale’s “Cassandra”, an influential text written in 1852 that advocates for women’s right to exert their passions, and with which Webster was probably familiar (Fiske 486). 
Circe’s implied sexual liberation touches upon another sensitive issue in an era in which women’s sexuality was not discussed openly (Sutphin 376).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Fiske, Shanyn. “Augusta Webster and the Social History of Myth.” *Women’s Studies*, vol. 40, no. 4, Routledge, 2011, pp. 469-490. doi.org/10.1080/00497878.2011.561745.</bibl><bibl>Nightingale, Florence. “Cassandra.” *Cassandra and Other Selections from Suggestions for Thought*, edited by Mary Poovey, Pickering &amp; Chatto, 1991, pp. 205-231.</bibl><bibl>Sutphin, Christine. “The Representation of Women’s Heterosexual Desire in Augusta Webster’s ‘Circe’ and ‘Medea in Athens’.” *Women’s Writing*, vol. 5, no. 3, 1998, pp.  373-393.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-pilfered-booties" from="#s-pilfered-booties" to="#e-pilfered-booties">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Isabel Maria Osuna Montilla</name><name>Sophia Smolinski</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-20</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#language">
                  <p>The adjective “pilfered” is a derivative from the verb to “pilfer” which means to steal (cf. “pilfer, *v*.” 1.a.). In the poem, the stolen “booties” describe any “[p]lunder, gain, or profit acquired in common and destined to be divided among the winners.” (“booty, *n*.1” 1.). The phrase is tautological.</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>“booty, *n*.1.” *OED Online*, Oxford University Press, December 2021, www.oed.com/view/Entry/21557. Accessed 24 February 2021.</bibl><bibl>“pilfer, *v*.” *OED Online*, Oxford University Press, December 2021, www.oed.com/view/Entry/143856. Accessed 17 December 2021.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#intratextuality">
                  <p>This tautological statement of one of the men stealing is followed by the description of yet another man “snatch[ing…] gems” (Webster 164). The concept of theft is thereby repeated three times in one line.</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="3">
                <div type="category" ana="#interpretation">
                  <p>The repetition of the concept of being stolen renders the action as an even worse crime, and, therefore, it highlights Circe’s interest in claiming that, when the men are transformed into pigs, she is just revealing their true nature: “[t]hen the next day the beast in them will wake” (160); “Change? There was no change; / only disguise gone from them unawares” (189-190). Circe, thus, puts the men themselves at fault for their transformation and avoids blaming herself.</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-sward" from="#s-sward" to="#e-sward">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Valeria Reichert</name><name>Sophia Smolinski</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-20</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#language">
                  <p>A sward is a “surface of soil covered with grass or other herbage”; for instance, “turf” or “greensward” (“Sward, *n*.” 2.b.).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>“Sward, *n*.” *Oxford English Dictionary*, Oxford UP, March 2024, 
doi.org/10.1093/OED/1548594544. Accessed 01 June 2024.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-there-will-be-storm-at-last-storm-glorious-storm" from="#s-there-will-be-storm-at-last-storm-glorious-storm" to="#e-there-will-be-storm-at-last-storm-glorious-storm">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Isabel Maria Osuna Montilla</name><name>Sophia Smolinski</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-20</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#language">
                  <p>By avoiding the use of an article, Circe does not predict one storm in particular but rather the generic category of “storm”. One effect of this is the loss of a temporal limit. “[A] storm” would have an ending, “storm” in general does not have a defined end but may, at least in theory, go on endlessly.</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#intratextuality">
                  <p>The word “storm” is repeated several times in the course of the poem (see lines 52-57; 60-64; and 132-137). Circe’s emphatic repetition of “storm” in this line suggests her excitement and celebration of the upcoming storm, which, she hopes, will break the “sickly sweet monotony” (32) (cf. [[monotony]]).</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#context">
                  <p>Stories of storms received great interest in Greek literature. In ancient Greece, a whole rhetoric of storms was introduced by Homer (see Fantham and Wertheimer). The function of the sea-storm’s rhetoric was two-fold: firstly, to position the author’s work within the epic tradition – every poet was trying to out-do the storm written by the other poet. Secondly, to show the hierarchical structure of the characters within the poem – gods like Poseidon usually send storms to make the heroes’ mortality more apparent (Biggs and Blum 162).

Homer’s *Odyssey* is considered the archetype of sea-storm stories. It narrates the return of the Greeks from Troy: during their journey, Odysseus and his men are threatened by a great storm sent by Zeus (Finley). 

Storms are also used in Greek myths to bring heroes to certain places. When the speaker of “Circe” says “coming–yes, coming with the rising wind” (133), she anticipates the arrival of several men, which is another reference to the *Odyssey*.</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Biggs, Thomas, and Jessica Blum. “Sea-storms in Ancient Epic.” *Structures of Epic Poetry*, edited by Christiane Reitz and Simone Finkmann, De Gruyter, 2019, pp. 125-168. doi.org/10.1515/9783110492590-043.</bibl><bibl>Fantham, Elaine, and Linda Wertheimer. “Storms and Floods in the Ancient World.” *NPR*, 1 October 2005, www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=4932120. Accessed 21 December 2021.</bibl><bibl>Finley, Jr. John H. “5. Odysseus’ Tale.” *Homer&apos;s Odyssey*, Harvard University Press, 2013, pp. 93-138. doi.org/10.4159/harvard.9780674333864.c5.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#form">
                  <p>The storm could also stand for “a metaphor for passionate or tumultuous emotion” (Ferber 236). In this case, the gathering storm that is described points to Circe’s increasing desire for an emotional change: “long for a tempest on me and grow sick / of resting” (63-64).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Ferber, Michael. *A Dictionary of Literary Symbols*. Cambridge University Press, 1999. *EBSCOhost*, search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=nlebk&amp;AN=120164&amp;site=ehost-live. Accessed 27 January 2022.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="3">
                <div type="category" ana="#interpretation">
                  <p>The storm in the poem will bring not only a change in the weather, turning the sky dark and raising strong winds, but will also bring a change to Circe’s isolation: see lines 229-231. 

The (potentially) unlimited duration of the storm (cf. Level 1 Language) points to a sense of long-lasting effects for Circe. That is to say, Circe’s upcoming change is understood to stay and accompany her, marking a new period in her life. 

The storm can be understood as a way of indicating Circe’s increasing sexual desire (see Circe’s erotic self-mirroring encounter: lines 115-126). Sutphin argues that Circe uses the gathering storm as a form of describing her sexual desire: it “allows her a rare consciousness and acceptance of her own sexuality” (374). Similarly, Fiske states that Circe’s longing for the violence of a storm is due to the recognition of her passionate nature (487): “[a]nd, if my heart must always be adrowse / in a hush of stagnant sunshine, give me then / something outside me stirring” (lines 50-52). The storm can therefore also be interpreted as a physical representation of Circe’s inner emotional turmoil.</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Fiske, Shanyn. “Augusta Webster and the Social History of Myth.” *Women’s Studies*, vol. 40, no. 4, Routledge, 2011, pp. 469-490. doi.org/10.1080/00497878.2011.561745.</bibl><bibl>Sutphin, Christine. “The Representation of Women’s Heterosexual Desire in Augusta Webster’s ‘Circe’ and ‘Medea in Athens.’” *Women’s Writing*, vol. 5, no. 3, Routledge, 1998, pp. 373-92.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
      </listAnnotation>
    </standOff>
</TEI>