<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Lines Composed a Few Miles abobe Tintern Abbey, On Revisiting the Banks of the Wye during a Tour. July 13, 1798</title>
          <author>William Wordsworth</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt><p>TEASys Viewer</p></publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc><p>Annotating Literature, Tübingen University</p></sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><anchor xml:id="s-lines-composed-a-few-miles-abobe-tintern-abbey-on-"/><anchor xml:id="s-lines"/><anchor xml:id="e-lines"/><anchor xml:id="e-lines-composed-a-few-miles-abobe-tintern-abbey-on-"/><anchor xml:id="s-five-years-have-past-five-summers-with-the-length-"/>Five years have past; five summers, with the length
Of five long winters! And again I hear
These waters, rolling from their mountain-springs
With a soft inland murmur.<anchor xml:id="e-five-years-have-past-five-summers-with-the-length-"/>—Once again
Do I behold <anchor xml:id="s-these-steep-and-lofty-cliffs"/>these steep and lofty cliffs<anchor xml:id="e-these-steep-and-lofty-cliffs"/>,
That on a wild secluded scene impress
Thoughts of more deep seclusion; and connect
The landscape with the quiet of the sky.
The day is come when I again repose
Here, under this dark sycamore, and view
These plots of <anchor xml:id="s-cottage-ground"/>cottage-ground<anchor xml:id="e-cottage-ground"/>, these orchard-tufts,
Which at this season, with their unripe fruits,
Are clad in one green hue, and lose themselves
&apos;Mid groves and copses. Once again I see
These hedge-rows, hardly hedge-rows, little lines
Of sportive wood run wild: these pastoral farms,
Green to the very door; and wreaths of smoke
Sent up, in silence, from among the trees!
With some uncertain notice, as might seem
Of vagrant dwellers in the houseless woods,
Or of some <anchor xml:id="s-hermits"/>Hermit&apos;s<anchor xml:id="e-hermits"/> cave, where by his fire
The Hermit sits alone.
                      <anchor xml:id="s-these-beauteous-forms"/>These beauteous forms<anchor xml:id="e-these-beauteous-forms"/>,
Through a long absence, have not been to me
As is a landscape to a blind man&apos;s eye:
But oft, in lonely rooms, and &apos;mid the din
Of towns and cities, I have owed to them,
In hours of weariness, sensations sweet,
Felt in the blood, and felt along the heart;
And passing even into my purer mind
With tranquil restoration:—feelings too
Of unremembered pleasure: such, perhaps,
As have no slight or trivial influence
On that best portion of a good man&apos;s life,
His little, nameless, unremembered, acts
Of kindness and of love. Nor less, I trust,
To them I may have owed another gift,
Of aspect more sublime; that blessed mood,
In which the burthen of the mystery,
In which the heavy and the weary weight
Of all this unintelligible world,
Is lightened:—that serene and blessed mood,
In which the affections gently lead us on,—
Until, the breath of this corporeal frame
And even the motion of our human blood
Almost suspended, we are laid asleep
In body, and become a living soul:
While with an eye made quiet by the power
Of harmony, and the deep power of joy,
We see into the life of things.
                        If this
Be but a vain belief, yet, oh! how oft—
In darkness and amid the many shapes
Of joyless daylight; when the fretful stir
Unprofitable, and the fever of the world,
Have hung upon the beatings of my heart—
How oft, in spirit, have I turned to thee,
O sylvan Wye! thou wanderer thro’ the woods,
     How often has my spirit turned to thee!
     And now, with gleams of half-extinguished thought,
With many recognitions dim and faint,
And somewhat of a sad perplexity,
The picture of the mind revives again:
While here I stand, not only with the sense
Of present pleasure, but with pleasing thoughts
That in this moment there is life and food
For future years. And so I dare to hope,
Though changed, no doubt, from what I was when first
I came among these hills; when like a roe
I bounded o’er the mountains, by the sides
Of the deep rivers, and the lonely streams,
Wherever nature led: more like a man
Flying from something that he dreads, than one
Who sought the thing he loved. For nature then
(The coarser pleasures of my boyish days
And their glad animal movements all gone by)
To me was all in all.—I cannot paint
What then I was. The sounding cataract
Haunted me like a passion: the tall rock,
The mountain, and the deep and gloomy wood,
Their colours and their forms, were then to me
An appetite; a feeling and a love,
That had no need of a remoter charm,
By thought supplied, not any interest
Unborrowed from the eye.— That time is past,
And all its aching joys are now no more,
And all its dizzy raptures. Not for this
Faint I, nor mourn nor murmur; other gifts
Have followed;for such loss, I would believe,
Abundant recompense. For I have learned
To look on nature, not as in the hour
Of thoughtless youth; but hearing oftentimes
The still sad music of humanity,
Nor harsh nor grating, though of ample power
To chasten and subdue.—And I have felt
A presence that disturbs me with the joy
Of elevated thoughts; <anchor xml:id="s-a-sense-sublime-of-something-far-more-deeply-inter"/>a sense sublime
Of something far more deeply <anchor xml:id="s-interfused"/>interfused<anchor xml:id="e-interfused"/>,
Whose dwelling is the light of setting suns,
And the round ocean and the living air,
And the blue sky, and in the mind of man:
A motion and a spirit, that impels
All thinking things, all objects of all thought,
And rolls through all things.<anchor xml:id="e-a-sense-sublime-of-something-far-more-deeply-inter"/> Therefore am I still
A lover of the meadows and the woods
And mountains; and of all that we behold
From this green earth; of all the mighty world
Of eye, and ear,—both what they half create,
And what perceive; well pleased to recognise
In nature and the language of the sense
The anchor of my purest thoughts, the nurse,
The guide, the guardian of my heart, and soul
Of all my moral being.
                       Nor perchance,
If I were not thus taught, should I the more
Suffer my genial spirits to decay:
For thou art with me here upon the banks
Of this fair river; <anchor xml:id="s-thou-my-dearest-friend-my-dear-dear-friend-and-in-"/>thou my dearest Friend,
My dear, dear Friend; and in thy voice I catch
The language of my former heart, and read
My former pleasures in the shooting lights<anchor xml:id="e-thou-my-dearest-friend-my-dear-dear-friend-and-in-"/>
Of thy wild eyes. Oh! yet a little while
May I behold in thee what I was once,
My dear, dear Sister! <anchor xml:id="s-and-this-prayer-i-make125-knowing-that-nature-neve"/>and this prayer I make,
Knowing that Nature never did betray
The heart that loved her;<anchor xml:id="e-and-this-prayer-i-make125-knowing-that-nature-neve"/> &apos;tis her privilege,
Through all the years of this our life, to lead
From joy to joy: for she can so inform
The mind that is within us, so impress
With quietness and beauty, and so feed
With lofty thoughts, that neither evil tongues,
Rash judgments, nor the sneers of selfish men,
Nor greetings where no kindness is, nor all
The dreary intercourse of daily life,
Shall e&apos;er prevail against us, or disturb
Our cheerful faith, that all which we behold
Is full of blessings. Therefore let the moon
Shine on thee in thy solitary walk;
And let the misty mountain-winds be free
To blow against thee: and, in after years,
When these wild ecstasies shall be matured
Into a sober pleasure; when thy mind
Shall be a mansion for all lovely forms,
Thy memory be as a dwelling-place
For all sweet sounds and harmonies; oh! then,
If solitude, or fear, or pain, or grief,
Should be thy portion, with what healing thoughts
Of tender joy wilt thou remember me,
And these my exhortations! Nor, perchance—
If I should be where I no more can hear
Thy voice, nor catch from thy wild eyes these gleams
Of past existence—wilt thou then forget
That on the banks of this delightful stream
We stood together; and that I, so long
A worshipper of Nature, hither came
Unwearied in that service: rather say
With warmer love—oh! with far deeper zeal
Of holier love. Nor wilt thou then forget,
That after many wanderings, many years
Of absence, these steep woods and lofty cliffs,
And this green pastoral landscape, were to me
More dear, both for themselves and for thy sake!
</div></body></text>
  <standOff>
      <listAnnotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-a-sense-sublime-of-something-far-more-deeply-inter" from="#s-a-sense-sublime-of-something-far-more-deeply-inter" to="#e-a-sense-sublime-of-something-far-more-deeply-inter">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>admin</name><name>Junwen Lu</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-16</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#context">
                  <p>According to W. J. B. Owen, this part is related to &quot;Aeneid VI, 724-7: ‘*caelum ac terram camposque liquentes / Lucentemque globum lunae Titaniaque astra / Spiritus intus alit, totamque infusa per artus / Mens agitat molem et magno se corpore miscet;* (‘an inner spirit sustains the sky and the earth and the watery plains, the bright globe of the moon, the sun and the stars, and mind activates the whole frame, pervading all its members, and blends with the great body&apos;)&quot; (qtd. in Owen 212).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Owen, W. J. B., ed. *Lyrical Ballads*. By William Wordsworth and Samuel Taylor Coleridge. Oxford University Press, 1969.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#interpretation">
                  <p>In the later 18th and early 19th centuries, Pantheism was widely spread, which is the belief that Nature is identical with God (Hoque 47); it includes the doctrine that &quot;God is everything and everything is God&quot; (&quot;pantheism, n. 1&quot;), and is usually accompanied by &quot;worship or […] love of nature&quot; (&quot;pantheism, n. 1&quot;). Wordsworth believed in Pantheism, and this belief is also expressed in &quot;Tintern Abbey&quot;, especially in lines 99-106. To him, Nature and God are one, which &quot;appears in different names like spirit, life beyond physical world, […] a living principle, an undistinguishable motion, […] etc.&quot; (Hoque 48-49).

Both &quot;Tintern Abbey&quot; and the passage in the *Aeneid* quoted in L1 - Context are about the relationship between nature, the human mind and spirit. The elements of nature that they refer to are similar as well. Moreover, both passages argue that nature and the mind have a common core that makes them exist and work; in other words, there is an inherent community between them.

The speaker realizes that, to perceive nature, not only nature itself is needed but also one&apos;s experiences and thoughts about nature - nature and mind are blended. Meanwhile, the past and the present are blended as well: the past does not end, it becomes an important part of life, and the nature in the speaker&apos;s memory is now mingled with the nature in front of him (Kelly).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Hoque, Muhammad Azizul. &quot;Pantheism in Wordsworth: A Study from the Islamic Perspective.&quot; *International Journal of Islamic Thought*, vol. 5, Jun. 2014, pp 45-55. </bibl><bibl>Kelly, David. &quot;An overview of ‘Lines Composed a Few Miles above Tintern Abbey&apos;.&quot; *Poetry for Students*, Gale. *Gale Literature Resource Center*, link.gale.com/apps/doc/H1420007980/LitRC?u=tuebi&amp;sid=LitRC&amp;xid=aa8b7196. Accessed 7 Mar. 2021.</bibl><bibl>&quot;pantheism, n.&quot; *OED Online*, Oxford University Press, July 2021, www.oed.com/view/Entry/136995. Accessed 20 July 2021.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-and-this-prayer-i-make125-knowing-that-nature-neve" from="#s-and-this-prayer-i-make125-knowing-that-nature-neve" to="#e-and-this-prayer-i-make125-knowing-that-nature-neve">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Junwen Lu</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-27</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#form">
                  <p>The word &quot;nature&quot; appears six times in this poem, and here it is capitalized for the first time.</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#context">
                  <p>These lines have been related to Coleridge&apos;s &quot;This Lime-Tree Bower&quot; (see Magnuson 153-54):

Henceforth I shall know
That nature ne&apos;er deserts the wise and pure;
No plot so narrow, be but Nature there,
No waste so vacant, but may well employ
Each faculty of sense, and keep the heart
Awake to Love and Beauty! and sometimes
‘Tis well to be bereft of promis&apos;d good,
That we may lift the soul, and contemplate
With lively joy the joys we cannot share. (61-69)</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor. &quot;This Lime-tree Bower my Prison.&quot; *Poetry Foundation*, www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/43992/this-lime-tree-bower-my-prison.</bibl><bibl>Magnuson, Paul. *Coleridge and Wordsworth: A Lyrical Dialogue*. Princeton University Press. 1988.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#interpretation">
                  <p>In these lines, &quot;Nature&quot; is personified, which may be related to Wordsworth&apos;s worship of nature and is also indicated in lines 156-157: &quot;and that I, so long / A worshipper of Nature&quot; (William and Coleridge 210). Combining lines 138-139: &quot;Our cheerful faith that all which we behold / Is full of blessings&quot; (William and Coleridge 209), which suggest that he and his sister believe that nature is full of blessings (Napierkowski and Ruby), nature now is associated with religion. Furthermore, both Wordsworth&apos;s and Coleridge&apos;s texts express that despite &quot;vacancy or loss&quot;, as long as they are still the lovers of nature, they are able to transmit joy (Magnuson 154).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Magnuson, Paul. *Coleridge and Wordsworth: A Lyrical Dialogue*. Princeton University Press. 1988.</bibl><bibl>Napierkowski, Marie Rose and Mary Ruby, editors. &quot;Overview: &apos;Lines Composed A Few Miles Above Tintern Abbey&apos;.&quot; *Poetry for Students*, vol. 2, Gale, 1998. Gale Literature Resource Center, link.gale.com/apps/doc/H1430001975/LitRC?u=tuebi&amp;sid=LitRC&amp;xid=1783e115. Accessed 7 Mar. 2021.</bibl><bibl>Wordsworth, William, and Samuel Taylor Coleridge. *Lyrical Ballads with A Few Other Poems*. J. &amp; A. Arch, 1798.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-cottage-ground" from="#s-cottage-ground" to="#e-cottage-ground">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Sandra Wetzel</name><name>Pavlina Papadopoulou</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-16</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#context">
                  <p>In the year 1798, when the poem was written, the region Wordsworth describes, was, in fact, an industrial one. However, he decides to disregard this fact throughout the poem, for the sake of his art and the particular poetics he pursued: according to Wu, the poet writes in the *Preface of Lyrical Ballads* that &quot;[l]ow and rustic life was generally chosen because in that condition the essential passions of the heart find a better soil in which they can attain their maturity, are less under restraint, and speak a plainer and more emphatic language&quot; (Wu 507).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Wu, Duncan, editor. *Romanticism: An Anthology*. 4th ed. Blackwell Anthologies, 2012.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#interpretation">
                  <p>The poem takes the stance that humanity can coexist with nature and need not interfere with it in any significant way. Signs of human habitation, such as &quot;cottage-ground&quot; (v.11), seem to blend in with the landscape which is portrayed as unaffected by human presence. Wu summarizes this stance as follows: &quot;Wordsworth thought his work engaged fully with life as it was lived&quot; (Wu 23).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Wu, Duncan, editor. *Romanticism: An Anthology*. 4th ed. Blackwell Anthologies, 2012.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-five-years-have-past-five-summers-with-the-length-" from="#s-five-years-have-past-five-summers-with-the-length-" to="#e-five-years-have-past-five-summers-with-the-length-">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Junwen Lu</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-16</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#form">
                  <p>These four lines contain enjambments, which means &quot;the continuation of a syntactic unit from one line to the next without a major juncture or pause&quot; (Brogan et al. 435-436).

Enjambments are one of the main elements of conversation poems.</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Brogan, T. V. F., et al. &quot;Enjambment.&quot; *The Princeton Encyclopedia of Poetry and Poetics*, edited by Roland Greene, Stephen Cushman, et al., Princeton University Press, 2012, pp. 435-436.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#interpretation">
                  <p>Here, enjambments may be used to highlight the excitement and pleasure of the speaker at seeing the natural scenery again, which cannot be expressed within one line. The content of the next line reinforces the feelings indicated in the previous one: &quot;with the length / Of five long winters!&quot; The word &quot;long&quot; shows that the speaker thinks five years quite a long time, and thus enhances his excitement at being here again after all this time. The gap in the middle of the sentence caused by the link break may also hint at the gap between the first time the speaker saw the scenery and the present time. &quot;These waters, rolling from their mountain-springs / With a sweet inland murmur&quot;: the enjambment in these two lines also emphasizes the speaker&apos;s pleasure at hearing the waters, which does not stop at the end of the first line but becomes more vivid in the next one, just like the waters roll from their spring, the words roll from line to line (the enjambment accordingly contributes to iconicity, the correspondence of form and content). Moreover, although the speaker&apos;s excitement and pleasure are already very clear in the previous lines: the use of &quot;sweet inland murmur&quot; is unexpected, and the continuation of the description here not only makes the scene more specific but potentially also contributes to the reader&apos;s immersion into the scene.</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-hermits" from="#s-hermits" to="#e-hermits">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Junwen Lu</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-16</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#language">
                  <p>&quot;Hermit&quot; refers to a person who lives a solitary life, with or without religious motives (&quot;hermit, n. 1&quot;).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>&quot;hermit, n.&quot; *OED Online*, Oxford University Press, November 2020, www.oed.com/view/Entry/86268. Accessed 10 November 2020.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#textual-variants">
                  <p>In the third edition of *Lyrical Ballads* (1802), the word &quot;hermit&quot; is capitalized, but it is not in the first (1798) and second (1800) edition.</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Wordsworth, William, and Samuel Taylor Coleridge. *Lyrical Ballads with A Few Other Poems*. J. &amp; A. Arch, 1798.</bibl><bibl>Wordsworth, William, and Samuel Taylor Coleridge. *Lyrical Ballads with Other Poems*. 2nd ed., Biggs and Co. Bristol, 1800.</bibl><bibl>Wordsworth, William, and Samuel Taylor Coleridge. *Lyrical Ballads with Pastoral and Other Poems*. Biggs and Cottle, 1802.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#interpretation">
                  <p>The image of the hermit indicates a comparison between the speaker and the hermit. The speaker lives in human society, while the hermit does not fit into human society; nature provides some kind of escape from every-day life for the speaker, while for the hermit nature is every-day life. Accordingly, the natural scenery perceived by the speaker is combined with his personal experience and thoughts, while the hermit &quot;has actual nature at his disposal&quot; (Kelly).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Kelly, David. &quot;An overview of ‘Lines Composed a Few Miles above Tintern Abbey&apos;.&quot; *Poetry for Students*, Gale. *Gale Literature Resource Center*, link.gale.com/apps/doc/H1420007980/LitRC?u=tuebi&amp;sid=LitRC&amp;xid=aa8b7196. </bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#questions">
                  <p>Why is the word &quot;hermit&quot; capitalized in the third edition of *Lyrical Ballads* (1802), while it is not in the first (1798) and second (1800) edition? Does this change have a different effect?</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-interfused" from="#s-interfused" to="#e-interfused">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>admin</name><name>Junwen Lu</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-16</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#language">
                  <p>Interfuse means &quot;to pour in&quot;, to infuse one thing into another (&quot;interfuse, v. 2&quot;).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>&quot;interfuse, v.&quot; *OED Online*, Oxford University Press, November 2020, www.oed.com/view/Entry/97796. Accessed 10 November 2020.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-lines-composed-a-few-miles-abobe-tintern-abbey-on-" from="#s-lines-composed-a-few-miles-abobe-tintern-abbey-on-" to="#e-lines-composed-a-few-miles-abobe-tintern-abbey-on-">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Pavlina Papadopoulou</name><name>Sophia Smolinski</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-20</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#context">
                  <p>In his Fenwick Notes, Wordsworth explains that: “No poem of mine was composed under circumstances more pleasant for me to remember than this: I began it upon leaving Tintern, after crossing the Wye, and concluded it just as I was entering Bristol in the evening, after a ramble of four or five days, with my sister. Not a line of it was altered, and not any part of it written down till I reached Bristol” (Wordsworth 66). This pleasure finds expression in many instances in his poem; it especially resonates with the speaker’s exclamation in the last two lines, which brings things full circle, referring from the title of the poem to its very ending:

“And this green pastoral landscape, were to me
More dear, both for themselves and for thy sake!” (*v*.162)</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Wordsworth, William. *The Fenwick Notes of William Wordsworth.* Edited by Jared R. Curtis. Pbk. ed. Humanities-Ebooks, 2008.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#form">
                  <p>The first two words of the title “Lines Composed” seem to be rather unspecified by Wordsworth himself and do not give any detailed hint as to the form and genre of the poem.</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#context">
                  <p>According to Wu, “[i]n conversation and correspondence Wordsworth and his circle usually referred to the poem as “Tintern Abbey”” (Wu 415). However, Tintern Abbey, except for in the title, is not mentioned again in the course of the poem.</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Wu, Duncan, editor. *Romanticism: An Anthology*. 4th ed. Blackwell Anthologies, 2012.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-lines" from="#s-lines" to="#e-lines">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Junwen Lu</name><name>Sophia Smolinski</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-20</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#form">
                  <p>The poem contains elements of different genres, such as ode, lyrical ballad, conversation poem, and landscape poem.

The poem is written in blank verse, i.e., in an iambic pentameter without any fixed rhyme scheme (cf. Friedberg 145-48).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Friedberg, Nila. “Blank Verse.” *The Princeton Encyclopedia of Poetry and Poetics*, edited by Roland Greene, Stephen Cushman, et al., Princeton University Press, 2012, pp. 145-148.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#form">
                  <p>The poem has generic similarities to the traditional ode form. This assumption is partly confirmed by Wordsworth’s note in *Lyrical Ballads*: 

I have not ventured to call this Poem an Ode; but it was written with a hope that in the transitions, and the impassioned music of the versification would be found the principal requisites of that species of composition. (Wordsworth 267) 

The “transitions” here may refer to the traditional structure of an ode, which consists of a strophe, an antistrophe and an epode. It then also refers to the “transitions of one verse paragraph to another” (Hartman 27). Another possibility is that it may refer to the transition of the traditional ode to a kind of poetry which derives from the ode but is combined with Wordsworth’s innovativeness; “Tintern Abbey” would be an example of this (Kneale 220).

The ode is “the most formal, ceremonious, and complexly organized form of lyric poetry, usually of considerable length” (Fogle and Fry 971). The eighteenth-century English ode originated from the ancient ode of Pindar, the characteristics of which are its use of imagery, varying but emotionally related subjects, “complex metrical organization” as well as its “emotional, exalted, intense” and “vertiginously changeable tone” (Fogle and Fry 971-72). The subject of each verse paragraph of Wordsworth’s poem has a different topical emphasis, but they are all associated with the love of nature. This fits with the feature of “varying but emotionally related subjects” of the traditional ode, but the tone of the poem is not as “exalted” and “intense” as that of a Pindaric ode. Here, especially in the fourth and fifth stanza, the tone is more tranquil and meditative. Moreover, a traditional ode is about the praise or commemoration of a person, thing, place, etc. (Fogle and Fry 971), but, in general, the theme of this poem is not merely praise for nature; it contains the idea of the connection between nature and life experience as well. Overall, compared with the traditional ode, the subjects of the poem have similar features, but the tone of it has its own characteristics, and the theme is rather complex.</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Fogle, Stephen F., and Paul H. Fry. “Ode.” *The Princeton Encyclopedia of Poetry and Poetics*, edited by Roland Greene, Stephen Cushman, et al., Princeton University Press, 2012, pp. 971-973.</bibl><bibl>Hartman, Geoffrey H. *Wordsworth&apos;s Poetry*, 1787-1814. Yale University Press, 1964.</bibl><bibl>Kneale, J. Douglas. “Wordsworth, Milton, and a Question of Genre.” *Modern Philology*, vol. 109, no. 2, Nov. 2011, pp. 197-220.</bibl><bibl>Wordsworth, William, and Samuel Taylor Coleridge. *Lyrical Ballads with Other Poems*. 2nd ed., Biggs and Co. Bristol, 1800.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="3">
                <div type="category" ana="#form">
                  <p>With the tone, which is not as exalted and intense as that of the traditional ode, the poem may also be classified as a conversation poem, which is “a type of informal, colloquial poem whose tone is meant to echo relaxed conversation” (Richardson and Bohn 304). Further, the “intimate tone” and the “relaxed, frequently enjambed blank verse” (Richardson and Bohn 304) found in the poem are also the main elements of conversation poems. Besides, this poem is mentioned as one of the examples of conversation poem in *The Princeton Encyclopedia of Poetry and Poetics*. 

 “Tintern Abbey” also contains elements of a landscape poem, which describes “nature and art, the actual world, and the world as it is seen in spatial extension and in imagination” (Costello 782). The poem fits this classification as it describes the landscape around the river Wye in detail and praises the beauty of nature in general.

The poem may also be described as a lyrical ballad, since it was first published in 1798 in *Lyrical Ballads*. Ballads are narrative poems that “present a series of actions involving protagonists” and “typically […] focus on a single episode” (Dugaw 114). This poem displays the speaker’s experience of a tour along the banks of the river Wye, but it is not as narrative as a typical ballad, because it is more about the speaker’s thoughts and feelings than his actions. What is more, ballads are usually written in quatrains, with an abac rhyme scheme, but this poem doesn’t have a fixed rhyme scheme.</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Costello, Bonnie. “Landscape Poem.” *The Princeton Encyclopedia of Poetry and Poetics*, edited by Roland Greene, Stephen Cushman, et al., Princeton University Press, 2012, pp. 782-783.</bibl><bibl>Dugaw, Dianne. “Ballad.”* The Princeton Encyclopedia of Poetry and Poetics*, edited by Roland Greene, Stephen Cushman, et al., Princeton University Press, 2012, pp. 114-118.</bibl><bibl>Richardson, Alan, and Willard Bohn. “Conversation Poem.” *The Princeton Encyclopedia of Poetry and Poetics*, edited by Roland Greene, Stephen Cushman, et al., Princeton University Press, 2012, pp. 304-305.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-these-beauteous-forms" from="#s-these-beauteous-forms" to="#e-these-beauteous-forms">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>admin</name><name>Sandra Wetzel</name><name>Pavlina Papadopoulou</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-16</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#context">
                  <p>Edmund Burke, who had published a treatise on aesthetics in 1757, has written on the idea of the aesthetic concept of the Beautiful: &quot;Beauty is, for the greater part, some quality in bodies acting mechanically upon the human mind by the intervention of the senses.&quot; (Burke, Part III, xii).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Burke, Edmund. *A Philosophical Enquiry into the Origin of Our Ideas of the Sublime and Beautiful*, (1757), Cambridge University Press, 2014.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#interpretation">
                  <p>Throughout the poem, from its to title to its very last lines – &quot;[a]nd this green pastoral landscape, were to me/ More dear, both for themselves and for thy sake!&quot; (v.162) –, nature is being revered. Its beauty is exciting pleasure on a physical and intellectual level, and this very beauty of nature should inspire love, even affection, in the observer and reader.</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-these-steep-and-lofty-cliffs" from="#s-these-steep-and-lofty-cliffs" to="#e-these-steep-and-lofty-cliffs">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Sandra Wetzel</name><name>Pavlina Papadopoulou</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-16</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#context">
                  <p>In this line – along with line 7: &quot;Thoughts of more deep seclusion&quot; –, an element of the Sublime makes its appearance as the description of nature evokes strong feelings of awe, and even terror. Edmund Burke, in his treatise on aesthetics in 1757, defines the Sublime as follows: &quot;Whatever is fitted in any sort to excite the ideas of pain and danger, that is to say, whatever is in any sort terrible, or is conversant with terrible objects, or operates in a manner analogous to terror, is a source of the sublime; that is, it is productive of the strongest emotions which the mind is capable of feeling&quot; (Burke 39).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Burke, Edmund. *A Philosophical Enquiry into the Origin of Our Ideas of the Sublime and Beautiful* (1757). Cambridge University Press, 2014.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#interpretation">
                  <p>Cliffs can be said to be among the most staggering parts of nature, their precipices impress into the landscape the power that nature holds. The mere sight of them can be said to take the observers (i.e. readers) into &quot;thoughts of more deep seclusion&quot; (v.7), inspired by the greatness and awe the cliffs represent. This very seclusion could also refer to the separation the cliffs provide. It is not just the vastness of cliffs that is so impressive but also the notion of dividing one thing from another, which may formerly have belonged together that leads to that feeling of &quot;seclusion&quot;.</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#intratextuality">
                  <p>The aesthetic concept of the Sublime is mentioned again in the poem, when the speaker comments that &quot;[t]o them [he] may have owed another gift, /Of aspect more sublime; that blessed mood&quot; (v. 37-38) and further down &quot;[a] presence that disturbs me with the joy / Of elevated thoughts; a sense sublime / Of something far more deeply interfused&quot; (v. 96-98).</p>
                  
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
          <annotation xml:id="ann-thou-my-dearest-friend-my-dear-dear-friend-and-in-" from="#s-thou-my-dearest-friend-my-dear-dear-friend-and-in-" to="#e-thou-my-dearest-friend-my-dear-dear-friend-and-in-">
            <respStmt><resp>annotator</resp><name>Junwen Lu</name></respStmt>
            <date>2026-03-27</date>
            
              <div type="level" n="1">
                <div type="category" ana="#context">
                  <p>This part can be related to John of Gaunt&apos;s speech in *Richard II*: &quot;This land [England] of such dear souls, this dear dear land – / Dear for her reputation through the world-&quot; (Shakespeare 2.1.40-68), a reading which may be based upon the repetitive &quot;dear&quot; (see Weinfield 269).

A second possibility is that the passage refers to the Song of Songs, near to the end of which &quot;the younger, virginal sister&quot; is also abruptly mentioned. In the Song of Songs, this expression appears in the context of the female lover wishing that she were her beloved&apos;s sister, because a brother-sister relationship allows them to kiss in public without being looked down upon (Pearson 210).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Pearson, Sara L. &quot;Allusive Pursuits: The Song of Songs in Wordsworth&apos;s &apos;Tintern Abbey&apos;.&quot; *Studies in Romanticism*, vol. 53, no. 2, 2014, pp. 195-216. Gale Literature Resource Center, link.gale.com/apps/doc/A386434143/LitRC?u=tuebi&amp;sid=LitRC&amp;xid=3a04d7fc. Accessed 7 Mar. 2021.</bibl><bibl>Shakespeare, William. *King Richard II*, edited by Charles R. Forker, The Arden Shakespeare, Bloomsbury, 2002.</bibl><bibl>Weinfield, Henry. &quot;‘These Beauteous Forms&apos;: ‘Tintern Abbey&apos; and the Post-Enlightenment Religious Crisis.&quot; *Religion and the Arts*, vol. 6, no. 3, Jan. 2002, pp. 257-290.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
              <div type="level" n="2">
                <div type="category" ana="#interpretation">
                  <p>The possible intertextual reference to John of Gaunt&apos;s speech indicates that the emphasis of &quot;Tintern Abbey&quot; has changed from nature, which is described in the first verse paragraph of the poem, to what is &quot;dear&quot; to the speaker. The reason why the landscape is important is not the place itself, but that it &quot;evokes feelings of love […] and reflections on our capacity to love&quot; (Weinfield 269-270).

In the Song of Songs, after a declaration about love, the character of a sexually immature sister is described who is far from ready for marriage. Similarly, in &quot;Tintern Abbey&quot;, Wordsworth likens his sister to his younger self, who is close to the innocence of childhood and away from the sexual consciousness of adulthood; he thus also underlines her role as a &quot;dear sister&quot;, a &quot;non-sexual role&quot; (Pearson 211), rather than that of a lover (Pearson 210-211). Thus, being her brother, as Pamela Woof explains in *Towards &quot;Tintern Abbey&quot;*, Wordsworth could share &quot;mind, heart and spirit&quot; but not &quot;body&quot; (49).

In addition, the speaker thinks that his sister &quot;sees what [his] younger [self] once saw, and feels what he felt&quot;, and this is the validation of the younger speaker&apos;s perceptions (Smith 315).</p>
                  <listBibl><bibl>Pearson, Sara L. &quot;Allusive Pursuits: The Song of Songs in Wordsworth&apos;s &apos;Tintern Abbey&apos;.&quot; *Studies in Romanticism*, vol. 53, no. 2, 2014, pp. 195-216. Gale Literature Resource Center, link.gale.com/apps/doc/A386434143/LitRC?u=tuebi&amp;sid=LitRC&amp;xid=3a04d7fc. Accessed 7 Mar. 2021.</bibl><bibl>Smith, Lyle H. &quot;Reading ‘Something&apos; in ‘Tintern Abbey&apos;.&quot; *Christianity &amp; Literature*, vol. 45, no. 3-4, June 1996, pp. 303–317.</bibl><bibl>Weinfield, Henry. &quot;‘These Beauteous Forms&apos;: ‘Tintern Abbey&apos; and the Post-Enlightenment Religious Crisis.&quot; *Religion and the Arts*, vol. 6, no. 3, Jan. 2002, pp. 257-290.</bibl><bibl>Woof, Pamela. &quot;Towards &apos;Tintern Abbey&apos;: The Poem.&quot; *Towards Tintern Abbey: A Bicentenary Celebration of &apos;Lyrical Ballads&apos;*, edited by Robert Woof and Stephen Hebron, The Wordsworth Trust,1998, pp. 43-60.</bibl></listBibl>
                </div>
              </div>
            
          </annotation>
        
      </listAnnotation>
    </standOff>
</TEI>